<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on David Fornborg</title>
    <link>https://dfornis.github.io/dfornis/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on David Fornborg</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dfornis.github.io/dfornis/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ex-post policy evaluation with the synthethic control method</title>
      <link>https://dfornis.github.io/dfornis/p/ex-post-policy-evaluation-with-the-synthethic-control-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dfornis.github.io/dfornis/p/ex-post-policy-evaluation-with-the-synthethic-control-method/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Randomly assigned controlled experiments are, naturally, a favored tool by scientists who want to make claims about causality in research. They are however expensive, impractical and often ethically dubious to run in a social science or policy context. Consider the country that randomly assigns its regions into a treatment and control group when implementing criminal justice reform, in order to find out if it has the intended effect, all else equal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What makes a plot go (semi)-viral?</title>
      <link>https://dfornis.github.io/dfornis/p/what-makes-a-plot-go-semi-viral/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dfornis.github.io/dfornis/p/what-makes-a-plot-go-semi-viral/</guid>
      <description>Background How long is the wait for a rental apartment in Stockholm? It&amp;rsquo;s an engaging question in the spotlight of both politics and daily life in the Swedish capital. In light of a recent surge in news articles about how young swedes struggle to enter the housing market, I took a look at data provided by Stockholms Bostadskö - Stockholm&amp;rsquo;s sole distributor of rental apartments. It tells a story about a deteriorating rental market with a rapidly growing wait time for apartments (Swedes queue for apartments: Soviet style).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data visualizations of 2021</title>
      <link>https://dfornis.github.io/dfornis/p/data-visualizations-of-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dfornis.github.io/dfornis/p/data-visualizations-of-2021/</guid>
      <description>While initially hesitant, owing to a sense that I would rather be involved in actual research, visualizing data turned out to be a creative outlet in the midst of more heavy data wrangling and theoretical work.
All visualizations were made in R with ggplot2.
Climate adaption The first set of visualizations were made from a large panel dataset on the climate adaption activities of international organizations, developed for a PHD thesis by Ece Kural.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nowcasting a leading economic indicator in times of uncertainty - with R</title>
      <link>https://dfornis.github.io/dfornis/p/nowcasting-a-leading-economic-indicator-in-times-of-uncertainty-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dfornis.github.io/dfornis/p/nowcasting-a-leading-economic-indicator-in-times-of-uncertainty-with-r/</guid>
      <description>Macroeconomic indicators are traditionally collected with a large lag. This limits their utility in times of high uncertainty. In a pandemic for example, infection rates may accelerate non-linearly (as seen in SIR-models) and are likely to react to variables such as temperature and degree of immunity, many of which remain unknown at the beginning of a pandemic. Nowcasting has been suggested by the Swedish Riksbank (Andersson, Reijer 2015) among others as a tool to make predictions with higher frequency data.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
